<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://janeyang07.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://janeyang07.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-23T16:47:17+00:00</updated><id>https://janeyang07.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal academic website showcasing research, publications, and professional work. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">I Don’t Know What I’m Doing, But I Keep Showing Up</title><link href="https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2026/i-dont-know-what-im-doing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Don’t Know What I’m Doing, But I Keep Showing Up"/><published>2026-02-15T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2026/i-dont-know-what-im-doing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2026/i-dont-know-what-im-doing/"><![CDATA[<p>February showed up before I was ready. It always does. The way deadlines creep, seasons shift, alarms ring when you swear you just closed your eyes.</p> <p>Somehow, without quite meaning to, I’ve become one of those people who say things like “the endgame of a PhD is becoming an athlete.” My life has narrowed to a simple rhythm: work, train, eat. Brain and body, both under renovation. Six to eight sessions a week. Four or five at CrossFit, another two or three for endurance work, shoulder to shoulder with people who’ve spent years competing. Retired pros. Current competitors. One of them is a reigning world champion in trail running. I stretch beside them and think: what am I doing here?</p> <p>Maybe that’s always the question, though. What am I doing here. In the lab, in the gym, in this life I’m assembling one rep at a time. Riding a wave of encouragement, I signed up for a DEKAFIT competition at the end of March. An impulse with a side of reckless hope. Will I hit my goal? No idea.</p> <p>Here’s what I’m learning. Showing up matters more than showing up perfectly. And showing up doesn’t have to mean leaving everything on the floor every time. The body isn’t a machine you run until it breaks. It needs rest the way a garden needs rain. I want fitness to teach me discipline, something I can carry into work, into writing, into daily life. But I also want to learn this: that showing up at 70% still counts. That progress isn’t linear. That the goal is to keep going, not to burn out trying.</p> <p>Sometimes I worry I’ll backslide into who I used to be, the round little potato version of me that stuck around for two decades. So I’m trying to document more. To notice small victories and actually write them down. Not because they’re impressive, but because they’re proof I’m still moving.</p> <p>I’m lucky not to be doing this alone. Grateful for the crew at Fortius and for my labmates. For family across the ocean and friends around the corner. For everyone who puts up with my rambling. And for the quiet things that keep me steady: mushrooms popping up after rain, animals crossing my path, Mochi at home enjoying her food without a care in the world. They don’t ask me how my dissertation is going. They just exist nearby, and that’s enough.</p> <p>I still don’t know what I’m doing. But I keep showing up.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="我不知道自己在做什么但我还在继续">我不知道自己在做什么，但我还在继续</h1> <p>转眼到了2026年的二月，我感觉措手不及。二月来得太快，就像截止日期总是悄然逼近，就像季节不声不响地更替，就像闹钟响的时候，总觉得还没睡够。</p> <p>新的一年，我误打误撞开始了”读博的尽头是体育生”的生活。除了工作就是训练，还有吃吃吃。大脑和身体，都在施工中。每周六到八次训练，四五次CrossFit，两三次耐力训练，和那些有多年专业比赛经验的运动员们一起。好多伙伴是退役的职业运动员，或者是现役运动员。其中一位是现在的越野赛世界冠军。我在他们身边热身，心里想：我在这里做什么？</p> <p>但也许这永远是那个问题。我在这里做什么。在实验室里，在健身房里，在这个我正一点一点搭建的生活里，一次动作，一次重复。在大家的鼓励下，我头脑一热报名了三月底的DEKAFIT比赛。那是一瞬间的冲动，带着莽撞的希望。到时候能不能达到目标？我不知道。</p> <p>我正在学习的是：出现比完美更重要，但出现不意味着每一次都要拼尽全力。身体不是一台需要被榨干的机器。它是一座花园，需要休息，也需要雨水。我想从健身中学会自律，把它带进我的工作、写作、日常。但我也想学会这件事：不完美地出现，也算出现。进步不是一条直线。目标是可持续的前行，而不是无止境的消耗。</p> <p>有时候我怕自己会退回去，变回那个圆滚滚的、躺平的旧版本，那个存在了二十多年的我。所以我想学会记录，把每一点小小的进步都写下来，庆祝那些微不足道的胜利。不是因为它们很大，而是因为它们证明我还在走。</p> <p>我很幸运，不是一个人在走这条路。感谢训练馆里的伙伴们，感谢实验室的同事们，感谢远方的家人，身边的朋友，感谢那些愿意听我絮叨的人。也感谢这个世界里安静的存在：雨后冒出来的蘑菇，路上偶遇的小动物，家里享受美食的Mochi。它们不问我论文写得怎么样，只是安静地陪着我。</p> <p>我不知道自己在做什么。但我会继续尝试。在健身房，在书桌前，在所有不确定的缝隙之间。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="crossfit"/><category term="training"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On training, showing up, and not burning out.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Coldest Summer I Ever Spent Was in London</title><link href="https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2026/coldest-summer-london-paris/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Coldest Summer I Ever Spent Was in London"/><published>2026-01-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2026/coldest-summer-london-paris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2026/coldest-summer-london-paris/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="paris-on-a-whim">Paris, on a Whim</h2> <p>I was in Europe for a conference and took a few days off to see Paris. The idea had been planted months earlier by <em>The Paris Novel</em>, a book whose food descriptions were so vivid I could practically taste them through the pages. Unlike the book’s protagonist Stella, though, I didn’t plan out any fine dining experiences. Most of the time I just wandered and looked up whatever nearby restaurant had good reviews.</p> <p>My favorite dish of the whole trip was a Burgundy-style salad with jambon persillé, which is basically a pork and parsley terrine with garlic, served cold. The vinaigrette had this bright acidity that made the whole thing feel refreshing and satisfying at the same time. It also made me finally understand why people pair wine with rich food. The natural acidity and aroma probably cuts through heaviness in the same way the vinaigrette did. Too bad I’m allergic to alcohol.</p> <p>Some days I played the role of Local Parisian, or at least my idea of one. I’d grab my “panda grocery bag” (a big tote my mom gave me that I bring literally everywhere), pick up a fresh baguette from the bakery, get some cheese and French butter weighed out at the fromagerie, grab some salami or ham, and head to a park to read and eat. I even got roped into a chess game with some locals. Other times I’d buy a crêpe and sit by the river, watching the boats go by, the pedestrians crossing the bridge, the diners at the restaurants on the opposite bank. Everyone seemed like the opening scene of their own story. What I didn’t expect was that eating outdoors in Paris makes you a target for wasps. They eye your food the way seagulls do, except wasps have zero concept of personal space.</p> <p>Over those few days I visited some classic landmarks and two museums, wandered through neighborhoods where centuries-old architecture sits right next to modern life, and flipped through ancient books at a community library. Paris is incredibly walkable and clearly designed with pedestrians in mind, which I loved.</p> <p>Oh, and a little saga. My Airbnb toilet clogged on night one. By 7:30 the next morning I was going door to door through every convenience store and mini-market in walking distance, asking for a plunger. Shop after shop: <em>“Euh… outside, outside…”</em> I finally found one at Monoprix, thanks to Reddit.</p> <p>At the register, I couldn’t help myself. I needed this cashier to understand what I’d just been through. So I’m slowly explaining in English that my toilet clogged the moment I arrived, that I’ve been to six stores already, waving the plunger around with one hand, slapping my forehead with the other. She didn’t get it at first, but then it clicked. She shook her head and went <em>“Oh la la!”</em>, did this whole motion of pulling her hair out, and wished me good luck.</p> <p>Then I walked back through the 16th arrondissement holding a bright red plunger aloft with a bag full of drain supplies, marching in the opposite direction of everyone quietly commuting to work. I must have looked like I was heading to storm the Bastille.</p> <h2 id="crossing-the-channel">Crossing the Channel</h2> <p>I’m writing this on the Eurostar, somewhere under the Dover Strait. In Paris I’d been surviving on broken French, aggressive hand gestures, and facial expressions doing about 80% of the heavy lifting. I wonder what London will be like.</p> <h2 id="london-in-three-days">London in Three Days</h2> <p>I landed in London and was immediately jumped by wind and “low temperatures.” Technically just the low teens Celsius, not actually cold, but without sun and with that wind, it felt like winter. For a second I thought I was back in a San Francisco summer. I wonder if Mark Twain would ever say: <em>The coldest winter I ever spent was a summer in London.</em> I panic-bought a jacket that afternoon and went straight to my Airbnb to make American chicken noodle soup, my personal cold-prevention ritual. The Airbnb had a cat named Dasheng (大圣, after the Monkey King), and honestly he was one of the best parts of the whole trip.</p> <p>My first feeling stepping into London was pure relief. I could speak English again.</p> <p>Right off the train platform I ran into someone improvising on a public piano, completely in their own world. Every Tube station had a different busker. A band here, a singer-songwriter there. I later found out London has a whole <em>Grassroots Music Tube Map</em> that documents the underground music scene station by station.</p> <p>I saw <em>Les Misérables</em> in the West End. Sat in the back of the stalls, didn’t matter. I cried multiple times. Having just been in Paris seeing the actual historical paintings in the museums made the whole thing hit differently.</p> <p>In Soho, I walked past the National Portrait Gallery during some kind of community sketching event, so I sat down and drew for a while with the materials they had out. Also in Soho, I made the mistake of peering curiously into the Nothing store and making eye contact with the staff. They waved me in and spent almost half an hour showing me every product they had. They knew I was an American tourist who wasn’t going to buy anything there, and they still gave me company merch and told me to just order online when I got home so I’d have a U.S. warranty. No pressure, just genuinely nice.</p> <p>Three days is nothing, obviously. But I kept running into these small moments, this casual, baked-in respect for art and music and people, that made me want to come back for much longer.</p> <h2 id="the-food-london-edition-yes-really">The Food, London Edition (Yes, Really)</h2> <p>I came to London a little worried about the food situation. The reputation precedes it. But actually? Everything I tried was good.</p> <p>I had Beef Wellington at a Gordon Ramsay restaurant. I will admit I was quietly hoping it would come out underdone so I could say <em>“It’s RAW!”</em> But no, it was annoyingly perfect. English breakfast, fish and chips, all solid, all comforting in that way where you didn’t realize you needed it until it was in front of you.</p> <p>I also reunited with an old friend I hadn’t seen in years (we were so excited we forgot to take a single photo, which I think says something). We did Brazilian barbecue together. Absolutely massive, and yeah, a bit more flavor than the British stuff, I won’t lie. Oh, and I discovered at the supermarket that Lay’s are called Walkers here. Same company, different name. The kind of thing you only learn by wandering grocery aisles in another country.</p> <hr/> <p>Two fast weeks in Europe, now back in San Diego. Already thinking about where to go next.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="travel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few days in Paris and London after a conference in Europe.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trust the Roots</title><link href="https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2025/trust-the-roots/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trust the Roots"/><published>2025-11-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2025/trust-the-roots</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://janeyang07.github.io/blog/2025/trust-the-roots/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s something about tending a struggling garden that puts things in perspective.</p> <p>This year, my garden has weathered everything. Heatwaves that scorched leaves to paper, storms that flattened stems, bunnies that nibbled seedlings down to nothing, red spider mites that clustered like dark thoughts, fungus creeping through the soil, nutrients leaching away until everything yellowed and faded. There were moments I thought nothing would make it. Some didn’t. I learned to grieve what couldn’t be saved and keep tending what remained.</p> <p>But the survivors are coming back. My sugar snap peas were barely clinging to life a month ago, thin and trembling. Now they’re unfurling new tendrils, reaching upward, beginning to fruit.</p> <p>Watching them recover has made me think about roots I didn’t know ran so deep.</p> <p>My grandparents were farmers and teachers in the mountains of Fujian province. They survived famine and somehow raised seven children, children scattered like seeds across relatives’ homes because there wasn’t room for everyone under one roof. My parents grew up in that village and clawed their way toward a different life through education, through sheer will, until they made it to the city. Then they planted me in American soil. I was 14, alone in an LA apartment they rented from across the ocean. They sent money, but I tended to everything else myself. A seedling transplanted mid-season, learning to grow in an entirely foreign climate.</p> <p>Three generations. A few decades. Each of us uprooted and replanted somewhere we didn’t recognize.</p> <p>Sometimes I look at what they endured and feel small. Why do I carry so much self-doubt, so much anxiety when things go wrong? I survived at 14 in a country I didn’t know. Wasn’t that enough? Why can’t I be as tough as they were? Maybe it was something about being closer to the earth, a farmers’ understanding that hardship is just weather, just seasons, just part of the cycle.</p> <p>But then I return to my garden, and I see it differently.</p> <p>My grandparents knew Fujian’s soil, its rhythms, its storms. My parents learned to navigate the path from village to city within the landscape they were born into. I’m learning to grow in yet another climate entirely. New soil, new seasons, new pests I’ve never encountered. The struggles shift with each generation: famine and scattered families, then the grinding journey from rural to urban, then a teenager alone in a strange land, and now these quieter invasions. Anxiety, doubt, the fear of not being enough.</p> <p>But struggle is struggle. Survival is survival. And I am still here, still growing.</p> <p>Resilience isn’t about never bending. It’s about weathering what comes, season after season, and trusting that recovery happens in its own time. It’s about offering myself the same patience I give my struggling plants. The same grace my grandparents must have whispered to themselves when crops failed, when seven mouths needed feeding and there was barely enough. The same grace I needed at 14, learning which way to grow toward light in unfamiliar air.</p> <p>The farmers’ spirit isn’t just toughness. It’s patience. It’s the belief that roots go deeper than what you can see, that growth happens underground long before anything turns green. It’s the willingness to plant again after everything dies. My anxiety isn’t weakness. It’s just another way of caring deeply about what I’m cultivating, about the ground they cleared so I could grow here.</p> <p>Sometimes you just need to let nature take its course. Trust the roots. Trust the season. Trust that you’re planted deeper than you know.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="相信根系">相信根系</h1> <p>照料一座挣扎求生的花园，总能让人看清许多事情。</p> <p>这一年，我的花园历经磨难——热浪将叶片炙成薄纸，暴雨摧折了茎秆，兔群啃噬幼苗至无，红蜘蛛如晦暗心事般密布枝头，真菌在土壤深处蔓延，养分渐渐流失，直到一切都褪成枯黄。曾有些时刻，我以为不会再有什么能活下来。确实有些没能活下来。我学会了哀悼那些无法挽回的，继续守护那些尚存的。</p> <p>但那些幸存者呢？它们正在复苏。一个月前，我的荷兰豆还奄奄一息，纤弱颤抖。如今它们舒展新生的卷须，向上攀援，竟已开始结果。</p> <p>看着它们渐渐恢复，让我思索起韧性这件事——思索那些我不曾察觉却早已深扎的根系。</p> <p>我的祖父母是福建山区的农人和教师。他们度过饥荒，抚养七个孩子长大——那些孩子像种子般散落在各家亲戚的屋檐下，因为自家的屋顶容不下所有人。我的父母在那个村庄长大，凭借教育和意志，一步步走向城市。而后他们将我种在美国的土地上。十四岁那年，我独居洛杉矶，住在他们从大洋彼岸租来的公寓里。他们寄来生活费，但其余的一切都要我独自照料——一株在生长途中被移栽的幼苗，在全然陌生的气候里学习如何生存。</p> <p>三代人，数十年。我们每个人都被连根拔起，重新植入陌生的土地。</p> <p>有时我凝视他们经历过的一切，会感到自己渺小。为何我背负如此多的自我怀疑，如此深的焦虑？我十四岁便在异国独自生活——这还不够吗？为何我无法像他们那般坚韧？或许是因为他们更接近大地，拥有农人的领悟——苦难不过是天气，是季节，是循环的一部分。</p> <p>但当我回到花园，我看见了别的东西。我的祖父母熟知福建的土壤，它的韵律，它的风暴。我的父母学会了在他们诞生的土地上，从乡村通往城市的路径。而我在这里，学习在截然不同的气候中生长——新的土壤，新的季节，从未遇见的病虫害。每一代人面对的挑战都在演变：饥荒与离散的家庭，然后是从乡村到城市的艰辛跋涉，然后是一个孤身异乡的少年，而今是这些更为隐匿的侵扰——焦虑、怀疑、对自己不够好的恐惧。</p> <p>但挣扎终是挣扎，生存即是生存。而我仍在这里，仍在生长。</p> <p>韧性不是从不弯折，而是经受一季又一季的风霜，相信复苏会在它自己的时辰降临。是给予自己如同给予那些挣扎植物般的耐心——如同我的祖父母在庄稼歉收时，在七张嘴需要喂养而几乎弹尽粮绝时，必定对自己低语过的那种宽慰。如同我十四岁时所需要的那种温柔，在陌生的空气里摸索该朝哪个方向寻找光明。</p> <p>农人的精神不仅是坚韧，更是耐心。是相信根系比可见之处更深，相信生长早在你看见新绿之前便已在地下静静发生。是在万物凋零后仍愿再次播种。我的焦虑并非软弱——它只是另一种深切关怀的方式，关怀我正培育的一切，铭记他们开垦出的土地，让我得以在此生根。</p> <p>有时你只需顺应自然的节奏。相信根系，相信季节，相信你扎根之深，远超你所知晓。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="gardening"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tending a struggling garden and thinking about resilience across generations.]]></summary></entry></feed>